Serge Durand

Software Engineer and Full Stack Developer

- sergedurand205@gmail.com
- https://serge.codes https://linkedin.com/in/ sergedurand205

SUMMARY

Pragmatic and experienced software engineer who is well-versed in technology and writing code to create reliable and user-friendly systems that solve interesting problems. I'm also a skilled leader who has proven the ability to educate and manage a team of professionals to build software.

EXPERIENCE

Open Source Maintainer

10/2022 - Present

URL Shortener - tinyy.ink | youtu.be/xX9J4LlkRl8

- Developed an open-source project that convert long links into shorter ones. It supports QR code generation and statistics with chart.js
- A Redis-based cache server is leveraged for high-performant and near real-time reads.
- Uses CAPTCHA to enhance security by preventing bots and DOS attacks.
- · Tech stack consists of Django, MySQL and TailwindCSS.

Senior Javascript Developer

06/2022 - 08/2022

Thesis Follow up - edc-stg.online | youtube.com/watch?v=cA_qa-z-ls

- Managed a team of 5 developers in the development of a University platform for postgraduate students, using the MERN stack
- Implemented a robust API for front and backend communication and raised throughput of CORS requests by over 30% by using a Priority Queue data structure to prioritize incoming server requests.
- Reduced completion date by 1 week by applying Agile methodologies and using Jira to track issues and project evolution.

Software Developer

12/2019 - 03/2022

TechniqConsulting

- Collaborated with product managers to re-architect a multipage web-app to a single page app, boosting yearly revenue by over 30%.
- Implemented CI/CD pipelines using Jenkins and GitHub Actions which enabled rapid prototyping and improved time-to-market by more than 50%
- Tested software for bugs and operating performance using tools like Jest, unittest and selenium, added documentation, and fixed bugs to increase efficiency by over 35%.
- Suggested using the appropriate technologies and tools per project which in turn increased time-to-production by over 2
 weeks.

Python Developer

06/2021 - 10/2021

CS Portal - camerschools.site | youtu.be/6LdmxpaATBs

- Developed a platform that offers many services to users such as a marketplace, Q/A section and discussion section, among others.
- Implemented a microservices architecture using Docker which uses a Postgres database, all served with Django.
- Used Amazon S3 to host static and media files, and deployed project on the cloud via Azure App Service.
- Scores 97% Performance, 94% Accessibility and 92% Best Practices on PageSpeed Insights.

EDUCATION

Computer Science 2022

University of Yaoundé 1 - Bachelor's degree

• I led a team that developed a platform for my university to follow up the thesis of postgraduate students.

CERTIFICATES

DevOps Essentials (IBM) 11/2022 - Present

Enslish Speaking - Expert (Emmersion)

12/2022 - 04/2023

SKILLS

Docker Nodejs & Expressjs

CI/CD & DevOps SQL & NoSQL

Python & Django Project Management

JavaScript & TypeScript Software Testing

Reactjs & Nextjs

LANGUAGES

English Native French Native